{"question": "What does the Family and Medical leave act provide?", "answer": "The Family and Medical Leave Act (FMLA) provides eligible employees up to 12 workweeks of unpaid leave a year, and requires group health benefits to be maintained during the leave as if employees continued to work instead of taking leave. Employees are also entitled to return to their same or an equivalent job at the end of their FMLA leave.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Who can take FMLA leave?", "answer": "In order to be eligible to take leave under the FMLA, an employee must:", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Does the time I take off for vacation, sick leave or PTO count toward the 1,250 hours?", "answer": "The 1,250 hours include only those hours actually worked for the employer. Paid leave and unpaid leave, including FMLA leave, are not included. ( Special hours of service rules apply to airline flight crew members. )", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Is my employer required to pay me when I take FMLA leave?", "answer": "The FMLA only requires unpaid leave. However, the law permits an employee to elect, or the employer to require the employee, to use accrued paid vacation leave, paid sick or family leave for some or all of the FMLA leave period. An employee must follow the employer’s normal leave rules in order to substitute paid leave. When paid leave is used for an FMLA-covered reason, the leave is FMLA-protected.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "When can an eligible employee use FMLA leave?", "answer": "A covered employer must grant an eligible employee up to a total of 12 workweeks of unpaid, job-protected leave in a 12 month period for one or more of the following reasons:", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Are there any restrictions on when an employee can take leave for the birth or adoption of a child?", "answer": "Leave to bond with a newborn child or for a newly placed adopted or foster child must conclude within 12 months after the birth or placement. The use of intermittent FMLA leave for these purposes is subject to the employer’s approval. If the newly born or newly placed child has a serious health condition, the employee has the right to take FMLA leave to care for the child intermittently, if medically necessary and such leave is not subject to the 12-month limitation.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Does an employee have to take leave all at once or can it be taken periodically or to reduce the employee’s schedule?", "answer": "When it is medically necessary, employees may take FMLA leave intermittently – taking leave in separate blocks of time for a single qualifying reason – or on a reduced leave schedule – reducing the employee’s usual weekly or daily work schedule. When leave is needed for planned medical treatment, the employee must make a reasonable effort to schedule treatment so as not to unduly disrupt the employer’s operation.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "What is a serious health condition?", "answer": "The most common serious health conditions that qualify for FMLA leave are:", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Am I required to prove that I have a serious health condition?", "answer": "An employer may require that the need for leave for a serious health condition of the employee or the employee’s immediate family member be supported by a certification issued by a health care provider. The employer must allow the employee at least 15 calendar days to obtain the medical certification.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "May I use FMLA leave when I am unable to work because of severe anxiety? I see a physician monthly for this condition to manage my symptoms.", "answer": "Yes. Assuming that you work for a covered employer and are eligible for FMLA leave, you may take leave if you are unable to work due to a serious health condition under the FMLA. A chronic condition whether physical or mental (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, anxiety, dissociative disorders) that may cause occasional periods when an individual is unable to work is a qualifying serious health condition if it requires treatment by a health care provider at least twice a year and recurs over an extended period of time.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Can my employer move me to a different job when I return from FMLA leave?", "answer": "On return from FMLA leave (whether after a block of leave or an instance of intermittent leave), the FMLA requires that the employer return the employee to the same job, or one that is nearly identical (equivalent).", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "What and when do I need to tell my employer if I plan to take FMLA leave?", "answer": "Employees seeking to use FMLA leave are required to provide 30-day advance notice of the need to take FMLA leave when the need is foreseeable and such notice is practicable. If leave is foreseeable less than 30 days in advance, the employee must provide notice as soon as practicable – generally, either the same or next business day. When the need for leave is not foreseeable, the employee must provide notice to the employer as soon as practicable under the facts and circumstances of the particular case. Absent unusual circumstances, employees must comply with the employer’s usual and customary notice and procedural requirements for requesting leave.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Are employers required to tell their employees of the existence of FMLA and the employee’s right to take FMLA leave?", "answer": "Every employer covered by the FMLA is required to post and keep posted on its premises, in conspicuous places where employees are employed, a notice explaining the FMLA’s provisions and providing information concerning the procedures for filing complaints of violations of the FMLA with the Wage and Hour Division. An employer that willfully violates this posting requirement may be subject to a civil money penalty for each separate offense. For current penalty amounts, see www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/applicable_laws . Additionally, employers must include this general notice in employee handbooks or other written guidance to employees concerning benefits, or, if no such materials exist, must distribute a copy of the notice to each new employee upon hiring.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "What is covered active duty?", "answer": "For a member of the Regular Armed Forces, covered active duty or call to covered active duty status means duty during the deployment of the member with the Armed Forces to a foreign country.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Are families of servicemembers in the Regular Armed Forces eligible for military caregiver leave?", "answer": "Yes. Military caregiver leave extends to those seriously injured or ill members of both the Regular Armed Forces and the National Guard or Reserves.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "What is the Uniformed Services Employment and Reemployment Rights Act (USERRA)?", "answer": "USERRA is a federal law that provides reemployment rights for veterans and members of the National Guard and Reserve following qualifying military service. It also prohibits employer discrimination against any person on the basis of that person’s past USERRA-covered service, current military obligations, or intent to join one of the uniformed services.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Who is an airline flight crew employee?", "answer": "An airline flight crew employee is an airline flight crewmember or flight attendant as those terms are defined in the FAA regulations.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "I am a caregiver for my brother who is not able to take care of himself. Can I take FMLA leave for his care?", "answer": "Maybe. FMLA leave to care for a relative is generally limited to caring for a spouse, son, daughter, or parent. An eligible employee standing in loco parentis to a sibling who is under 18, or who is 18 years of age or older and incapable of self-care because of a mental or physical disability, may take leave to care for the sibling, if the sibling has an FMLA-qualifying serious health condition.", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "What happens if I am mistreated for taking FMLA leave or if I am denied FMLA leave?", "answer": "Your employer is prohibited from interfering with, restraining, or denying the exercise of FMLA rights, retaliating against you for filing a complaint and cooperating with the Wage and Hour Division (WHD), or bringing private action to court. You should contact the WHD immediately if your employer retaliates against you for engaging in any of the legally protected activities. For additional information, call our toll-free information and helpline, available 8 a.m. to 5 p.m. in your time zone, 1-866-4-USWAGE (1-866-487-9243).", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
{"question": "Who do I contact if I need additional information or I want to file a complaint?", "answer": "If you have questions, or you think that your rights under the FMLA may have been violated, you can contact the Wage and Hour Division (WHD) at 1-866-487-9243. You will be directed to the WHD office nearest you for assistance. There are over 200 WHD offices throughout the country staffed with trained professionals to help you. To find the one nearest you, go to http://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/america2 .", "source": "https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla/faq"}
